Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, good שבעה עשר בתמוז נדחה, Shiv'ah Asar
B'Tammuz Nid'cheh, I guess. צום, Tsom,
יש לנו yesh lanu שבעה עשר בתמוז. Shiv'ah Asar B'Tammuz. We pick
up on the bottom of נ"ג עמוד ב', nun-gimmel amud-bet, נפל לתוכו
שור וכלים ונשברו. nafal l'tocho shor ve-kelav venishbaru.
So we are now dealing, continuing to move on with issues in
the משנה. Mishnah. We had a great debate of רבי נתן Rebbi
Natan and the רבנן Rabbanan about whether about a בור bor that
creates a תקלה takalah like a tripping hazard, but not an injury
hazard, or the reverse, an injury hazard without a tripping hazard, and
whether that's which which of either of those is considered a בור
bor to be חייב chayav for. And for רבי נתן Rebbi Natan
when two people participate or two entities in a damage whether they're
both considered to have proportional obligation or each one is fully obligated
but they pay proportionally and the ramifications of that when you can't
collect from one can you go to the other. Now we continue
in the משנה Mishnah where the משנה Mishnah just quoting from the
משנה Mishnah where it just speaks about finally in the משנה Mishnah
the basic principle we've been saying from day one which is that
a well is exempt, a בור bor is exempt for כלים kelim
that get damaged in it. So נפל לתוכו שור וכלים ונשברו, nafal
l'tocho shor ve-kelav venishbaru, it says that you are liable for the
ox and the donkey but you're exempt for the vessels that broke.
Five lines from the bottom on נ"ג עמוד ב'. nun-gimmel amud-bet. מתניתין
דלא כרבי יהודה, Matnisin d'lo k'Rebbi Yehuda, and our משנה Mishnah is
not like רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. We've been quoting a position of
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda that argues on the exemption of כלים kelim
and here it is.
דתניא בתורתא, De-tanya b'torata, רבי יהודה מחייב על נזקי כלים בבור. Rebbi
Yehuda mechayev al nizkei kelim ba-bor. מאי טעמא דרבנן? Mai ta'ama d'rabbanan?
What's the reason of the רבנן? Rabbanan? דאמר קרא, D'amar kra, the
verse says ונפל שמה שור או חמור—an ve-nafal shammah shor o chamor
ox or a donkey falls in. שור ולא אדם חמור ולא כלים,
shor v'lo adam chamor v'lo Kelim, an ox meaning not a person
and a donkey meaning not vessels, right. ורבי יהודה, Ve-Rebbi Yehuda, רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda would say no, או o לרבות את הכלים. l'rabot
et hakelim. שור או חמור, Shor o chamor, so או חמור o
chamor means don't just preoccupy it as something literally an animal here,
things associated like on an animal, the vessels also would be included.
By the way, we will see as the next פרק perek which
primarily focuses on אש esh that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda also, for
example, rejects other exemptions like a fire is exempt for things that
were טמון, tamun, buried, not גלוי, galui, exposed, and רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda says that no you don't have that exemption. So רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda seems in general not to be happy with these relatively
arbitrary exemptions by the categories of the ארבעה אבות נזיקין. arba avot
nezikin. You know why are you exempt for כלים? kelim? Let's actually
take a moment because we've been saying it from day one but
haven't really discussed it. Why are you exempt for כלים kelim and
why are you exempt for אדם adam by a בור? bor? So
exempt for אדם, adam, right, for אדם adam you can understand and
in a way actually it's not even a special exemption the way
תוספות Tosafot says it because for אדם adam you're חייב chayav for
injury, you're only exempt for a death and תוספות Tosafot has been
also pointing out from day one that even without any principles of
קים ליה Kim Lei there's a fundamental principle that there's no like
civil payment, you know, for the death of a human being. So
it's really not even a special הלכה halakha by בור bor if
you think about it, right? It's okay, by שור shor there's an
idea of כופר. kofer. So I guess you could sort of say
why isn't there an idea of כופר kofer but we've been seeing
by שור shor for example that it's כמיתת הבעלים כמיתת השור, kamitat
habalim k'mitat hashor, it's almost looked at as a type of like
you could imagine a person doing an act of murder, right, and
that's why the שור shor would have to be בכוונה, bekavana, there's
all these other requirements. So you don't even have that active act,
you know, by the בור. bor. But fundamentally the idea is is
that there's no civil payment by the death of a human and
that's why רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda doesn't disagree with that. The question
really is, and that's why רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda doesn't disagree with
that, the question is what's the exemption of כלים. kelim. And it
seems to be, you know, that one way of understanding this is
that כלים kelim don't have to be brought to the well, they
don't come to the well on their own. So if you see
the well as creating a hazard for the things that are like,
you know, you've now done something that like anything, you know, that
that is a hazard for anything that will come its way, okay,
but the כלים kelim don't on their own come its way. So
it's only sort of like indirectly a hazard for the כלים, kelim,
they have to be brought there by an animal.
So somehow indirectly causing damage, is that what you're saying?
Well the whole thing is indirect at all, like the whole גרמא
grama anyway, but the degree to which it's like a one degree
removed from your action, okay? This well is a direct threat to
things that are moving around in its vicinity, right? So it's only
an indirect threat to things that are moving things that are, you
know, that are carrying things that are in its vicinity.
But why חייב chayav you for making this מכשול הרבים? michshol harabim?
They should be חייב chayav in כלים kelim the other way around.
What? We could say the no the תורה Torah is דווקא davka
exemption.
I understand, there's no חידוש chiddush to say why you're חייב. chayav.
I'm trying to give some explanation to why you should be פטור,
patur, okay, to to at least appreciate that there's a degree of
indirectness to the degree to which this presents a threat to the
כלים kelim than it does to, you know, things that are moving
and can actually directly come to the בור. bor. So that's the
רבנן Rabbanan and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda disagrees. ורבנן, Ve-Rabbanan, and the
רבנן Rabbanan would say או, o, no the או o is not
coming to include כלים, kelim, top of נ"ד עמוד א', nun-dalet amud-alef,
או מיבעי ליה לחלק o mibaye lei le-challek שור או חמור shor
o chamor to distinguish שור או חמור shor o chamor
that you don't have to. both of them to fall in. ורבי
יהודה, V'Rabbi Yehuda, לחלק מונפל נפקא. l'chaleik mive-nafal nafka. No,
because it has ונפל ve-nafal the singular, ונפל שמה שור וחמור. ve-nafal
shama shor v'chamor.
Sometimes a ו' vov is used as the word to mean or,
and he says here you didn't need the word או, o, a
ו' vov could have served the meaning of the word or, because
the word נפל nafal is in the singular. ורבנן V'Rabbanan and the
Rabbis would say back, ונפל טובא משמע, ve-nafal tuva mashma, no, נפל
nafal could be used even when many things, many, you know, it's
a singular verb, but it could be used for many things. רש"י
Rashi gives you an example. Look at רש"י Rashi כמו ואתה בצלאל
ואהליאב, kemo ve-ata Betzalel v'Oholiav, ובא האות והמופת. u-va ha-ot v'ha-mofet.
So sometimes the תורה Torah uses a singular verb by talking about
two things, especially if those two things are somewhat like seen as
a group or as a unit. Now here they're not seen as
a unit. Okay, but nevertheless, the Rabbis say that's that would not
have done it by itself. You needed the או o to separate
the two. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, now the גמרא Gemara
has a different question. אימא ונפל כלל שור וחמור פרט. eima ve-nafal
klal shor v'chamor prat.
Why do we read this, before you get to כלים? keilim? How
do you know to include anything that's not an ox or a
donkey? Let's say ונפל ve-nafal is a general statement, שור וחמור shor
v'chamor is a specific, כלל ופרט אין בכלל אלא מה שבפרט. klal
u-prat ein ba-klal ela mah she-ba-prat. כלל ופרט klal u-prat you only
have the concrete, the specific, שור וחמור אין shor vechamor in, מידי
אחריני לא. midi achrinei lo, Maybe
you're only liable on an ox and a donkey. אמרי, Amri, no,
בעל הבור ישלם ba'al ha-bor yeshaleim חזר וכלל. chozar v'chalal.
So it says if an ox falls there, שור וחמור, shor v'chamor
בעל הבור ישלם, ba'al ha-bor yeshaleim, which is read as a general
statement. Again, it's not sort of a general statement de-gradually, it could
mean pay for what was just described, but again, it's read as
like you'll always pay, it suggests general liability. So חזר וכלל. chozar
v'chalal. כלל ופרט וכלל אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט. klal u-prat
u-klal ee ata dan ela k'ein ha-prat. So you have a general,
ונפל, ve-nafal, specific, שור וחמור, shor v'chamor, בעל הבור ישלם ba'al ha-bor
yeshaleim a general. So now you're going to say that that includes
anything similar to the specific and the concrete. אי אתה דן אלא
כעין הפרט. ee ata dan ela k'ein ha-prat. מה הפרט מפורש בעלי
חיים, mah ha-prat meforash ba'alei chayim,
so the same way the concrete is animals, אף כל בעלי חיים,
af kol ba'alei chayim, all animals. So that by the way, that's
another way you would exclude כלים, keilim, right? You would basically say,
שור וחמור shor v'chamor, become a כלל ופרט וכלל, klal u-prat u-klal,
so it has to be animals, and כלים keilim is you don't
have to make it like a like a technical word, oh, חמור
ולא כלים. chamor ve-lo kelim, It's that I mean in a way
maybe that's what חמור ולא כלים chamor v'lo keilim. means, but here
it's done through more normal hermeneutics that we're used to. It has
to be similar to שור shor and חמור. chamor. Okay, we'll see.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, but the גמרא Gemara isn't done
before you get to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the גמרא Gemara says,
wait, wait, I don't buy how you can get everything, all animals
out of that. אי מה הפרט מפורש דבר שנבלתה מטמאה במגע ובמשא.
ee mah ha-prat meforash davar she-neveilatah metama b'maga u-v'masa. Let me say
a different one. שור וחמור shor v'chamor two types of animals that
their carcass causes טומאה tumah when you touch and carry them. אף
כל דבר שנבלתה מטמאה במגע ובמשא. af kol davar she-neveilatah metama b'maga
u-v'masa.
Let me limit it to those types of things. What would that
exclude? עופות לא, ofot lo, not birds. Dead birds are I know
it's an arbitrary distinction, but on the other hand you could say
the likelihood, it's actually I mean, even though the idea that is
the נבילה מטמאה neveilah metama seems a relatively arbitrary point, the degree
to which a well is a hazard for birds is, you know,
how's a well a hazard for birds? I mean there are animals
that don't fly like the road runner or something. I guess it's
a hazard for them. What?
Maybe the הבל. hevel.
The הבל hevel is a hazard for them, right, but you would
wonder like why can't they fly out of it or something? Anyway,
so it's not so crazy to think you'd be exempt on birds
in a
well. Okay, so עופות לא. ofot lo. So let's say you're not
חייב chayiv for birds. No. אם כן נכתוב רחמנא חד פרטא. im
kein nichtov Rachmana chad prata. No, no. The fact that it says
שור או חמור shor o chamor tells you to make a broader
type of a category and not to exclude birds. But it says
one minute, that's not enough to tell me to include birds. הי
נכתוב, hei nichtov, which one do you think it could have said
and which would have been insufficient? אי כתב שור, ee ktav shor,
had it just written an ox, הוה אמינא קרב לגבי מזבח אין
שאין קרב לגבי מזבח לא. hava amina kareiv legabei mizbeiach in she-ein
kareiv legabei mizbeiach lo. Maybe only for animals that could be brought
as a sacrifice. Again, this seems totally bizarre. Why should the liability
for נזק nezek have to do with whether you can bring an
animal for a sacrifice? ואי כתב רחמנא חמור, v'ee ktav Rachmana chamor,
had it just written a donkey, הוה אמינא קדוש בבכורה אין שאין
קדוש בבכורה לא. hava amina kadosh bivchora in she-ein kadosh bivchora lo.
Only animals that have a sanctity of a firstborn. So which is
like, okay, a חמור chamor and a שור shor and a say
yes, but not for example, not kosher animals. Okay, so what? גמל.
gamal. גמל, gamal, right, exactly. We talked about גמל. gamal. So therefore
you have to say שור וחמור shor v'chamor to broaden it, but
maybe it's not so broad to include birds. How do you know
to include birds? אלא אמר קרא המת יהיה לו, ela amar kra
ha-meit yihyeh lo, כל דבר מיתה. kol davar mita. Fine, it's not
a כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u-prat u-klal. You're right, כלל ופרט וכלל
klal u-prat u-klal we would not get big enough to include birds.
It's because of the end of the פסוק, pasuk, המת יהיה לו
ha-meit yihyeh lo is says anytime something dies you're going to have
to pay. So that includes everything. Okay, and that's why we had
to then exclude
כלים. keilim. בין לרבנן דקא ממעטו להו לכלים ובין לרבי יהודה דקא
מרבו להו לכלים. bein l'Rabbanan d'ka mema'atu lehu l'keilim u-vein l'Rabbi Yehuda
d'ka marbu lehu l'keilim. כלים בני מיתה נינהו? keilim bnei mita ninhu?
So the גמרא Gemara says, I don't get it, because if המת
יהיה לו, ha-meit yihyeh lo, if that's in the end where we're
where our base is to say like that's how you know fundamentally
the things you're liable for, anything that dies. Why did you need
a special פסוק pasuk to exclude כלים? Kelim? כלים Kelim don't die.
And why did רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda need the word או? O?
That's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. Why, we've been
saying that from the beginning but now we're figuring it out. Why
do you need the word או O for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
to include כלים? Kelim?
Fundamentally, המציה לו Hamtzeya lo only makes sense why you need the
word או O to include because they don't die. But okay, but
how does the word או O include כלים Kelim if fundamentally כלים
Kelim don't die, they should be
basically,
categorically excluded? So the גמרא Gemara says,
no, אמרי Amri שבירת כלים, shviras Kelim,
I mean אמרי, Amri, yes, you could say שבירתם זו היא מיתתם.
shvirasam zo hi misasam. Yeah, when they break, that's considered to be
essentially their death. And by the way, although the גמרא Gemara doesn't
fully spell this out here, רש״י Rashi constantly spells it out, that's
why you're liable when a person gets injured because the exclusion that
we learn about שור ולא אדם shor v'lo adam is only for
the case of מיתה, misa, המציה לו. Hamtzeya lo. Injury you're חייב
chayav for for a person. Okay, but כלים Kelim are excluded for
all cases because even their injury is considered their death. Now, I
know sometimes a כלי kli breaks a little bit and still some
and still functional. But that's what the גמרא Gemara says. So therefore
כלים Kelim
are מיתה misa includes, excuse me, מיתה misa includes the death of
people and the breaking of כלים. Kelim. And then the words שור
וחמור shor v'chamor for the רבנן Rabbanan exclude the death of people.
Injury of people is still included and exclude any type of breakage
of כלים, Kelim, any type of damage of כלים. Kelim. And רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says no, no, no, we're going to include כלים
Kelim because the extra word או. O. Yes, go ahead.
So broken כלים Kelim are not susceptible to contracting טומאה? tumah?
Oh, there you go. Yes, but again, one could imagine like a
not fully broken,
damage without being broken.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, אמרי Amri
רב דאמר בור שחייבה עליו תורה Rav d'amar bor shechiyva alav Torah
who was mentioning הבל hevel before, somebody about the birds. According to
רב Rav that says that the בור bor that the תורה Torah
obligated for להבלו ולא לחבטו l'hevelo v'lo l'chavaso is a case of
הבל. hevel. להבלו l'hevelo is the real obligation. חבטה chavata by itself
is not enough. בין רבנן ובין לרבי יהודה Bein Rabbanan u'vein l'Rabbi
Yehuda כלים בני חבטה נינהו? Kelim b'nei chavata ninhu? So according to
רב, Rav, I don't get it.
How does a כלי kli break for הבל? hevel? You could talk
about a person or an animal inhaling this bad air, but how
does a כלי kli break from הבל hevel that the תורה Torah
would need to exclude it with the דרשה derasha of חמור ולא
כלים? chamor v'lo keilim They should have been excluded for רב Rav
in general because הבל hevel doesn't affect them. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, אמרי, Amri, you cannot get away from this הבל. hevel.
אמרי בחדתי דמיפקעי מהבלא. Amri b'chadti d'mifka'ei mehavla. Yes, if you have
a brand new
כלי kli then the הבל hevel will actually cause it to shatter.
Okay, this heavier air. So that could happen to a כלי kli
as well. So therefore it could have been you could have been
חייב chayav for a כלי. kli. And for רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
you are חייב chayav for a כלי kli for רב Rav if
it's a new כלי. kli. I guess now we're finding out for
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda you would be פטור pattur for an old
כלי kli because it would be impervious to the הבל. hevel. But
that's why since it's possible the הבל hevel could affect it, you
could be חייב chayav and that's why the rabbis needed the חמור
ולא כלים chamor v'lo Kelim? to exclude כלים. Kelim. Jono, it looks
like you have a question there.
Does someone not say something about why a new vessel would be
more susceptible to shattering?
I don't know, don't like... Doesn't it... It hasn't been tried and
true. No, I mean, I guess because I'm thinking about like pottery
things and things that just when they're I don't know, I guess
it's true, like if it's metal you wouldn't expect that, but like
if it's something like pottery wouldn't you expect that it would have
be more a little bit delicate after it was just came out
of the oven, no? I don't know.
הוה אמינא hava amina literally
exactly, like how new is new? Right, right. Yeah, I don't know,
you're right, I don't know. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
האי
והמת יהיה לו מיבעי ליה, Hai v'hamess yihyeh lo mibaya leh, one
minute, the גמרא Gemara says we're not done. So now we're saying
והמת יהיה לו v'hamess yihyeh lo includes anything not limited to שור
וחמור. shor vachamor שור וחמור shor vachamor. though, so it's like a
כלל ופרט וכלל, klal u'prat u'klal, you start with an everything is
included and then שור וחמור shor vachamor are coming to somehow limit
it. So שור ולא אדם חמור ולא כלים, shor velo adam chamor
velo kelim. and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't limit כלים Kelim because
he has the word או. O. So according to רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda we're going to ask what is the word חמור chamor doing
for him if it's not excluding
anything? Okay, but people are excluded from death and כלים Kelim are
fully excluded. What? We have to have... well that's true, I don't
know, right. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
והאי והמת יהיה לו מיבעי ליה לכדרבא, v'hai v'hamess yihyeh lo mibaya
leh l'chideRava, one minute, you need והמת יהיה לו, v'hamess yihyeh lo,
you can't come to tell me that it fundamentally tells me you're
חייב chayav for everything. You need it for what רבא Rava says.
דאמר רבא שור פסולי המוקדשין, D'amar Rava shor psulei hamukdashin, remember this
from yesterday? The animal that was a sacrifice that got a blemish
and was redeemed and that you can't make use of the
carcass. שנפל לבור פטור, Shenafal l'bor pattur, שנאמר והמת יהיה לו, Shene'emar
v'hamess yihyeh lo, that the carcass is his, the owner's. למי שהמת
שלו, L'mi shehamess shelo, only a carcass that can be used by
the owner. If it can't be used by the owner like this
פסולי המוקדשין, psulei hamukdashin, you're fully exempt. יצא זה שאין המת שלו.
Yatza zeh she'ein hamess shelo. So if that's true, where do you
go ahead and have this פסוק pasuk that fundamentally includes everything? Anything
that dies? So אלא אמר קרא, ela amar kra, כסף ישיב לבעליו,
kesef yashiv liv'alav, you should pay money to the owners, לרבות כל
דאיתא בעולם. l'rabos kol de'isa ba'olam. So that's the general פסוק. pasuk.
Anytime that there's anything that has owners you have to pay for
it. אי הכי אפילו כלים ואדם נמי. i hachi afilu keilim v'adam
nami. So okay, so now back to, so now that we've got
this general פסוק pasuk of כסף ישיב לבעליו, kesef yashiv liv'alav, so
pay for כלים keilim and pay for כלים keilim and אדם. adam.
I don't know if an אדם adam has owners, but anyway, pay
for כלים. keilim. I guess so, that's a good point. אמר קרא
שור ולא אדם חמור ולא כלים. amar kra shor v'lo adam chamor
v'lo keilim. Now that we have a general פסוק pasuk whether it's
והמת יהיה לו v'hames yihyeh lo or whether כסף ישיב לבעליו, kesef
yashiv liv'alav, now we start with everything and we get שור וחמור
shor vachamor to come to exclude a person and כלים. keilim. So
לרבי יהודה דקמרבי ליה לכלים, l'Rabbi Yehuda d'kamarbei lei l'keilim, according to
Rabbi Yehuda
that says the או o comes to include כלים, keilim, בשלמא שור
מאי ממעט אדם. bishlama shor mai m'ma'et adam. We understand that a
שור shor was needed to exclude people. אלא חמור מאי ממעט. ela
chamor mai m'ma'et. Why did you need the word או o to
include כלים keilim and to neutralize the word חמור? chamor? Don't say
חמור chamor and don't say או o and just say שור shor
and you would exclude אדם adam and you'd have everything else included.
Is everybody with me?
They're thinking about כלל ופרט? klal u'frat?
No, you have והמת יהיה לו v'hames yihyeh lo or you have
כסף ישיב לבעליו, kesef yashiv liv'alav, so what you don't understand why
you need the חמור chamor and then the או o to neutralize
it. אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava, so Rava says you're right,
חמור דבור לרבי יהודה, chamor d'vor l'Rabbi Yehuda, the word חמור chamor
in the context of the well for Rabbi Yehuda, ושה דאבידה לדברי
הכל, v'seh d'aveidah l'divrei hakol, the word שה seh when it comes
to the אבידה aveidah because it says על כל דבר פשע, al
kol d'var pesha, no that's another פסוק, pasuk, it says what's the
פסוק? pasuk? חמור ושור
ושה ושלמה על כל אבידה, chamor v'shor v'seh v'salmah al kol aveidah,
whatever, what's the פסוק? pasuk? כי יאמר כי הוא זה, ki yomar
ki hu zeh, but that is that the אבידה aveidah פסוק pasuk
or that's the... yeah but anyway, but it's anyway whatever, there's a
פסוק pasuk that lists all these things it says על כל אבידה,
al kol aveidah, yeah I think it is כי יאמר כי הוא
זה, ki yomar ki hu zeh, anyway so you don't understand it
says כל אבידה, kol aveidah, why do you need the word שה?
seh? Like other words we do something with, but the word שה
seh seems extra. So the גמרא Gemara says קשיא. kashya. So we
don't know what those words are doing, like what the purpose, halachic
function of those words are. The word חמור chamor for Rabbi Yehuda
and the word שה seh for, for in general for the case
of אבידה, aveidah, especially since it's got a פסוק pasuk that says
על כל אבידה. al kol aveidah. By the way though I should
say that even though the גמרא Gemara here says that כסף ישיב
לבעליו kesef yashiv liv'alav is how we sort of know everything...
right well yeah that's true...
but anyway but the problem is that in the end it really
is from והמת יהיה לו v'hames yihyeh lo because that's how we
know that by an אדם adam you're still liable for injury, you're
only exempt for death. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, נפל לתוכו שור חרש שוטה וקטן חייב, nafal l'socho shor cheresh
shoteh v'katan chayav, this has got to be the funniest idea well
or just description. If an ox that is a חרש שוטה וקטן
cheresh shoteh v'katan falls in you're חייב. chayav. Okay, the ox is
a deaf-mute, or minor, or whatever. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי
שור חרש שוטה וקטן? mai shor cheresh shoteh v'katan? What does the
שור shor of שור חרש שוטה וקטן shor cheresh shoteh v'katan mean
says the גמרא? Gemara? אילימא שור של חרש שור של שוטה שור
של קטן ilima shor shel cheresh shor shel shoteh shor shel katan
owned by a חרש, cheresh, שוטה, shoteh, or a קטן? katan? So
okay you're חייב. chayav. Okay, like since when are we, why would
I think you would be exempt for destroying property of a חרש
שוטה וקטן? cheresh shoteh v'katan? And not only that, not only why
would I have thought you would have been exempt, it says האי
שור של פיקח פטור? hai shor shel pike'ach patur? You want to
tell me if it's a שור shor owned by a person who's
you know an adult with you know able to hear and whatever
and see and so on you tell me that you'd be פטור?
patur? Why would you be פטור patur by a normal שור? shor?
I don't know, see if they're leading the שור shor then you
might be able to, I don't know, maybe.
אמר רבי יוחנן שור שהוא חרש שור שהוא שוטה שור שהוא קטן.
amar Rabbi
Yochanan
shor she'hu cheresh shor she'hu shoteh shor she'hu katan.
It doesn't mean who it was owned by, it means that the
שור shor itself is a חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh v'katan. So
it's too bad that Rabbi Dov is not here because he's been
waiting the whole time we've been learning בבא קמא Bava Kamma to
point out, oh that's an oxymoron. So okay, a שור shor that's
a שוטה. shoteh. Okay anyway so the גמרא Gemara says האי שור
שהוא פיקח? hai shor she'hu pike'ach? One minute, פטור? patur? The גמרא
Gemara says I don't get it, so if it's like if it's
if it's an ox that doesn't have any of these issues it's
פטור? patur? Why is that? Why would an ox that you know
that's of right mind and so on why would that be exempt
and an adult? אמר רבי ירמיה לא מבעיא קאמר. amar Rabbi Yirmiyah
lo mibaya ka'amar. No no no, you are חייב chayav by a
פיקח. pike'ach. It goes without saying. לא מבעיא שור פיקח דחייב. lo
mibaya shor pike'ach d'chayav. Of course a normal שור shor you'd be
חייב. chayav. אבל שור חרש שוטה וקטן אימא חרשותו גרמה לו קטנותו
גרמה לו ליפטר. aval shor cheresh shoteh v'katan eima charshuso garma lo
katuso garma lo l'pater. Maybe you should be exempt if it's a
חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh v'katan. Maybe it's sort of like it
did it to itself. You know, it's like my my well wasn't
a hazard, the animal like like you know, the animal like threw
itself into the well or whatever, it didn't know what it was
doing. Of course like it's actually right it's more of a hazard
because they're not able to control what they're doing. But anyway, but
maybe you would have thought that you could have said that and
gotten off. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that you can't get
off of that. But אה"נ echi nami you're really חייב chayav for
everything. What's the גמרא Gemara saying that? It could have said it
about the case of who owned... If it's owned by a חרש
שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh ve-katan and you know and of course if
it's owned by a פיקח pike'ach you're חייב chayav but even if
it's owned by a חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh ve-katan. Of course
even there you would have said like what's the חידוש chiddush who
owns the property? Of course I should be חייב chayav regardless. Anyway
אמר ליה אביי לרבינא Amar lei Abaye le-Ravina והתניא נפל לתוכו בר
דעת פטור. ve-hatanya nafal le-tocho bar da'at pattur. But one minute. We
have an explicit ברייתא braita that says that if an intelligent being
falls in you're exempt. So מאי לאו שור בר דעת, mai lav
shor bar da'at, doesn't that mean that if an ox that's intelligent
falls in you're exempt? So the גמרא Gemara says שור בר דעת.
shor bar da'at. אמר ליה לא אדם. Amar lei lo adam. No
no no, it means if a person falls in you're exempt. אלא
מעתה אדם בר דעת הוא דפטור. Ela me-ata adam bar da'at hu
de-pattur. So only if a person is of their right mind are
you exempt. הלאו בר דעת הוא דחייב? ha-lav bar da'at hu de-chayav?
Would you tell me that if an אדם adam who is not
of their like you know fully of their right mind or you
know fully mature mind you'd be חייב? chayav? So what would happen
if you had a if you know a baby fell in? What
would happen if a person who was not mentally well fell in?
Why are you telling me you'd be חייב chayav only if they're
if only if they're בר דעת? bar da'at? But that's not true.
שור ולא אדם כתיב. Shor ve-lo adam ketiv. It's a categorical exemption
for people who fall in the well, even if the person is
not a בר דעת. bar da'at. אלא מאי בר דעת? Ela mai
bar da'at? So fine but what does בר דעת bar da'at mean?
מין בר דעת. min bar da'at. It doesn't mean the actual person
has to be a בר דעת. bar da'at. It means people. בר
דעת Bar da'at is a way of describing human beings in contrast
to animals. Right? Intellectual I mean you know intelligent you know beings
although I don't want to get into the whole animal rights issue
or whatever, animals are intelligent or not. But you know people used
to say right you know intelligent animal you know like what not
an animal what was the word? Anyway but they had a way
of describing what was the word what was the word they described
between like well you know human beings are a type of an
animal no. Intelligent being maybe? Anyway okay I don't know anyway. But
basically it's a way of saying you know yeah like you know
somebody who is a human being בר דעת bar da'at is a
way of describing a human being, not that this particular person has
דעת. da'at. Okay so yes all that means just to say is
that you're exempt for humans. It does not mean to talk about
it does not mean to talk about animals that have that are
intelligent or not intelligent. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this
I guess an intelligent being. Okay אלא מעתה אדם בר דעת? Ela
me-ata adam bar da'at? It was saying מין בר דעת. min bar
da'at. אמר ליה Amar lei no you can't say that. והתניא Ve-hatanya
we have a more explicit ברייתא. braita. It says נפל לתוכו שור
בן דעת פטור. nafal le-tocho shor ben da'at pattur. It's explicit. If
an ox that's intelligent falls in you're פטור. pattur. So you read
that together with our ברייתא braita about חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh
ve-katan and clearly it's our משנה Mishnah clearly it's saying that an
ox that's a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh ve-katan you're חייב chayav
and an ox that's intelligent you're פטור. pattur. Which is shocking. All
this time we talk about חייב chayav for a well and now
we find out for your standard case you're exempt if the animal
knows what it's doing. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר רבא
ela amar Rava fine. שור והוא חרש שור והוא שוטה שור והוא
קטן דוקא. Shor ve-hu cheresh shor ve-hu shoteh shor ve-hu katan davka.
That's only the case you're חייב chayav for. אבל שור והוא פיקח
Aval shor ve-hu pike'ach if the שור shor is you know of
right mind and knows what it's doing פטור pattur you're exempt. מאי
טעמא? Mai ta'ama? דבעי ליה עיוני ומזל. de-ba'ei lei ayyunei u-mazal. It
should have looked where it's going. Okay and it doesn't mean like
it has a legal responsibility. Animals don't have a legal responsibility to
do anything. But it means that you could say this was not
a hazard to animals. Animals who are during you know who are
normal animals will see it as long I mean if it's exposed.
If it's not exposed it would be a hazard right? If you
put like leaves and branches and made it into a trap of
course you'd be חייב. chayav. But if it was obvious and it
was visible then you could say this was not a hazard to
animals to normal animals. It was only a hazard to animals who
could not know what you know who weren't you know mature enough
or smart enough to know what they were doing. One minute תניא
נמי הכי tanya nami hachi we taught similarly נפל לתוכו שור חרש
שוטה וקטן. nafal le-tocho shor cheresh shoteh ve-katan. Now here we have
some other examples of when you'd be חייב. chayav. סומא Suma if
the animal's blind ומהלך בלילה u-mahalekh ba-laylah or at nighttime חייב. chayav.
Those cases you'd be חייב. chayav. But פיקח pike'ach if it has
all of its senses and it's and it's intelligent you know whatever
it's not of right mind ומהלך ביום u-mahalekh ba-yom and it's going
in the daytime פטור pattur exempt and ומהלך ביום u-mahalekh ba-yom right.
So in those cases that's the case then you'd be פטור pattur
when the when you know for a normal animal in the daytime
or whatever it would know to avoid this. I still wonder about
the קטן. katan. You'd think that small animals also instinctively know how
to avoid these things. So the קטן's katan still a funny. But
anyway did you want to say something? Just as anyone seen a
Far Side comic where there's like just a blank desert and a
cactus a guy riding a horse and he goes straight into the
cactus and like the thought bubble above the horse is like that's
it now I'm driving? Right exactly exactly. So the animals will know
to avoid it. So it's pretty funny. Not only are you exempt
for אדם adam and you're exempt for כלים. kelim. It's a little
disturbing I must say you know because here somebody makes this public
hazard and first of all you have all these positions that say
you're exempt if it's ברשות הרבים. bi-reshut ha-rabbim. You're only חייב chayav
if it's in your own רשות. reshut. And then we find out
that you're exempt for people you're exempt for כלים. kelim. The only
thing you're חייב chayav for is for animals animals and even animals
only like if they don't really know can't see and you know
don't know what they're doing. But if it's daytime and they can
see you know for a normal animal you'd be you'd be פטור.
pattur. So I guess I'm asking
I'm wondering what about people? What about people that you're חייב chayav
for injuries? injury? Are you חייב, chayav, right, logically you would say,
well, even the injury that I'm חייב chayav for people shouldn't apply
if it's daytime and if it's a person that has their senses
and their wits about them, right? So is that true? I don't
know. I don't know, I'd have to look it up, but it's
pretty interesting about how more and more we limit your liability by
this, right?
What about American law?
Yeah, I don't think so. You do a public hazard, it's all
very nice, you could say you should watch where you're going. You
shouldn't have made a hazard in the public domain, you know? That
seems to be more of the liability.
Okay, what was like the thought process behind why you'd be exempt
in the public domain because...
Yeah, because if you need it to work within the category of
ממון המזיק mamon hamazik and as some אדם המזיק adam hamazik it's
a גרמא. grama. And if you need it to work within the
category of ממון המזיק, mamon hamazik, so you don't own it. That's
the logic. I mean, whether it makes sense or not. Let me
just see if I can just quickly look at the רמב"ם Rambam
here and see if he says anything
about what do you call it, about if a person falls in
ביום bayom etc. Logically it would be the same, but still, I
mean, so many exemptions we wind up having.
Hello. Okay, so the רמב"ם Rambam limits it. This is nice. The
רמב"ם Rambam limits it because the רמב"ם Rambam apparently was also bothered
by the degree of exemption. The רמב"ם Rambam limits it to a
case where the animal died. He says to be such a hazard
that would cause death, right, and the animal then then you would
really have to say that the animal would like that that
meaning, it's the combination of, if the animal just got injured, you
could say if it was enough of a hazard even for normal
animals to cause injury, you can't say the animal should have totally
avoided it. But to have been such an, I guess the presumption
being like you have to be completely oblivious to like be going
full speed ahead. I'm not sure. Somehow it has to be a
bigger hazard.
Wait, so when are you חייב? chayav?
So you're exempt for the case of an animal that's a פיקח
pikeach if the animal dies. But if the animal is injured, the
רמב"ם Rambam because again the standard פסוק pasuk is talking about המת
יהיה לו hamet yiheyeh lo about death. But if the animal is
injured, then even if it was a פיקח pikeach you're going to
be חייב. chayav. So the point being to be such a tragic
end, at least a smart animal during the daytime or whatever should
have been able to avoid that drastic of an end. So that
also explains that you'd be חייב chayav by a person who got
injured, even an intelligent person normal, whatever person. So the רמב"ם Rambam
limits it to the case of death. And by the way, his
explanation is מפני שדרך הבהמה לראות ולסור מן המכשולים. mipnei she'derech habehema
lirot velasur min hamichsholim. Okay,
but he says, I'll just read you: ואם הוזק בה אדם או
הבהמה הפיקחית חייב נזק שלם. ve'im huzak bah adam o habehema hapikchit
chayav nezek shalem. Okay,
so the רמב"ם Rambam limits limits this extreme limitation because we're it's
getting smaller and smaller the cases that you're חייב chayav for. So
now at the end of the day, you're exempt for כלים, keilim,
you're exempt for death of a person, you're חייב chayav for animals
and injury of a person, but only if they are don't know
what they're doing or it's nighttime. But the רמב"ם Rambam says that's
only for death that that would get you off the hook. But
for injury, it wouldn't matter daytime or night time or whatever, you'd
be חייב chayav for everything. I mean, be חייב chayav even for
intelligent animals and people and so on. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, next משנה. Mishnah. אחד שור ואחד כל בהמה,
echad shor ve'echad kol behema, now although the פסוק pasuk talks about
a שור וחמור, shor v'chamor I mean we already just had a
דרשה drasha to broaden it, but the משנה Mishnah now is saying,
it's not limited to an ox, it includes any animal. לנפילת הבור,
linefilat habor, and that's true when it comes to falling into a
well, ולהפרשת הר סיני, ve'lehafrashat Har Sinai, which is not a הלכה
למעשה, halacha le'maaseh, when it says that you have to keep the
keep the לא תגע בו יד, lo tiga bo yad, what's the
פסוק pasuk
exactly? אם בהמה אם איש לא יחיה. im behema im ish lo
yichyeh. Right. אם בהמה אם איש, im behema im ish, so it'll
be all animals. Of course there it says אם בהמה. im behema.
Okay. Why are we mentioning הפרשת הר סיני?
hafrashat
Har Sinai?
Because it
says it's just throwing everything together that mentions animals and to tell
you don't limit it. ולתשלומי כפל, u'letashlumei kefel, to
pay double, ולהשבת אבידה, ve'lahashavat aveidah, although it mentions שור ושה וחמור,
shor vaseh vechamor, don't limit it to those
animals. ולפריקה ולחסימה, u'leferika u'lechassima, to the idea that you have to
if an animal is collapsing under its burden, to unload it. The
Torah speaks about a שור וחמור shor vechamor, I think. ולחסימה, u'lechassima,
muzzling it. לא תחסום שור בדישו, lo tachsom shor bedisho, you're not
allowed to muzzle an ox. It's not limited to an ox. ולכלאים,
u'lekilayim, crossbreeding. Now there's two types of crossbreeding, there's crossbreeding in terms
of actual breeding, and there's two types of כלאים, kilayim, there's crossbreeding
and there's plowing with a
שור וחמור יחדיו. shor vechamor yachdav. Okay, now once we're going to
not limit it to a שור וחמור shor vechamor and so on,
you're going to have to define what defines a different מין min
for כלאים, kilayim, right, because that's like, otherwise you could just say,
yeah, all animals. But here once you say all animals, it's not
enough because this is a category which actually distinguishes between categories of
animals. So you're going to have to figure out how do you
draw the lines between different species of כלאים. kilayim. ולשבת uleshabbat and
that it's digress on שבת. Shabbat. וכן חיה ועוף כיוצא בהן vechen
chaya ve'of kayotzei vahen
and not only including a בהמה behema because down on הר סיני
Har Sinai it says כל בהמה, kol behema, right? אם בהמה אם
איש. im behema im ish. But it also includes not only not
only like you know domesticated animals but even wild animals and even
birds. אוקיי okay אם כן למה נאמר שור וחמור? im ken lama
ne'emar shor vechamor? So why by the well does it say שור
וחמור? shor vechamor Some of these it doesn't say שור וחמור, shor
vechamor? a lot of them it says שור וחמור. shor vechamor, So
why does it say that? אלא שדיבר הכתוב בהווה, ela shediber hakatuv
behoveh, but yeah, it's just giving you a common scenario. It doesn't
mean to exclude, which is sort of different than what we said
before in the גמרא, Gemara, which is שור וחמור shor vechamor. coming
to exclude שור shor ולא אדם adam חמור ולא כלים. chamor v'lo
Kelim So this really seems to be a different type of an
approach and according to this you don't know like why we're excluding
אדם and כלים. kelim. אוקיי okay let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. ולנפילת הבור, ulenefilat habor, so how do you know not to
limit it to שור וחמור shor vechamor by the case of the
well? כסף ישיב לבעליו, kesef yashiv lev'alav, כתיב כל דאית ליה בעלים.
ketiv kol d'it lei be'alim. That's what we concluded at the end
of the previous סוגיא. sugya. והמת יהיה לו vehamet yihyeh lo but
כסף ישיב לבעליו. kesef yashiv lev'alav. Anytime that there's an owner you're
going to pay. אוקיי okay כדאמרן k'damran like we said earlier. ולפרישה
מהר סיני ulferisha mehar sinai that they have to separate from הר
סיני. Har Sinai. There it says בהמה behema but how do you
know to include a חיה chaya and עוף? of? So there it
says אם בהמה אם איש לא יחיה. im behema im ish lo
yichyeh. וחיה בכלל בהמה היא vechaya bichlal behema hi and a חיה
chaya whenever it says בהמה behema it's not doesn't have to be
read to be in the narrow sense of domesticated, it could mean
any beast even a wild beast. אוקיי. okay. אם, im, how do
you know to include birds? אם בהמה אם im behema im לרבות
את העופות, lerabot et ha'ofot, even birds. ולתשלומי כפל, uletashlumei kefel, pay
double. כדאמרינן k'damrinan על כל דבר פשע al kol devar pesha כלל.
klal. כל דבר פשע kol devar pesha כל דבר פשיעה. kol devar
peshi'ah. It just says על כל דבר פשע אשר יאמר כי הוא
זה עד האלוהים יבוא דבר שניהם אשר ירשיעון אלוהים ישלם שנים לרעהו.
al kol devar pesha asher yomar ki hu zeh ad ha'elohim yavo
devar sheneihem asher
yarshi'un elohim yeshalem shenayim lere'ehu. So that's a person that claims that
an object has been has been burgled and that person if he's
found to lie pays double. אוקיי okay so the same way if
you actually burgle an item you pay double but because but that's
a case where because it says על כל דבר פשע, al kol
devar pesha, all matter of guilt, and we're reading all matter of
like negligence anyway, the כל kol comes to include any type of
an item, not limiting to animals. אוקיי okay והשבת אבידה vahashevat aveidah
because it says לכל אבידת אחיך, lechol aveidat achicha, all lost animals
of your friend. There also doesn't even say animals, it says או
שמלה, o simlah, right, like on a garment. אוקיי okay so clearly
it's obviously very inclusive there. And that's why by the way we
notice here we don't have to like include חיה chaya and עופות
ofot because for כפל kefel and what do you call it and
השבת אבידה hashevat aveidah it's not even limited to living things, right,
it includes all objects, all things. אוקיי okay לכל אבידת אחיך. lechol
aveidat achicha. ופריקה, ufrikah, how do you know to unload the animal
that's collapsing under its burden? ילפינן חמור חמור משבת yalfinan chamor chamor
mishabbat because there it says כי תראה חמור אחיך, ki tir'eh chamor
achicha, right, רובץ תחת משאו. rovetz tachat masa'o. So because by שבת
Shabbat we're going to learn that the חמור chamor by שבת Shabbat
includes all animals, we link it to the case of שבת Shabbat
and include all animals. We'll get to שבת Shabbat in a minute.
וחסימה, vachasimah, it says לא תחסום שור בדישו, lo tachsom shor bedisho,
don't muzzle an ox. ילפינן שור שור משבת yalfinan shor shor mishabbat
because by שבת Shabbat it says שור shor and that means all
animals. So we're holding off for שבת. Shabbat. לכלאים, lekilayim, how about
כלאים, kilayim, mixing breeds? אי כלאים דחרישה, ei kilayim decharishah, if it
means plowing with them together, ילפינן שור שור משבת. yalfinan shor shor
mishabbat. It says שור וחמור יחדיו shor vechamor yachdav and we learn
from שבת Shabbat both שור shor, and חמור chamor suggest all animals.
אי כלאים דהרבעה, ei kilayim deharva'ah, if it's crossbreeding, ילפינן בהמתך. yalfinan
behemetcha. It says בהמתך לא תרביע כלאים. behemetcha lo tarbi'a kilayim. So
there it is, a generic בהמתך. behemetcha. But how do you know
to include birds, how do you know to include חיה? chaya? So
ילפינן בהמתך בהמתך משבת. yalfinan behemetcha behemetcha mishabbat. אוקיי okay because by
שבת Shabbat the same way there's שור וחמור shor vechamor it also
says בהמה, behema, so all these are words it says by שבת
Shabbat and we're going to learn by שבת Shabbat that all animals
are included. וגבי שבת מנלן, vegabi shabbat minalan, how do you know
by שבת? Shabbat? דתניא רבי יוסי אומר משום רבי ישמעאל, detanya rabbi
yose omer mishum rabbi yishmael, בדיברות הראשונות נאמר bedibrot harishonot ne'emar עבדך
ואמתך ובהמתך. avdecha va'amatecha uvehemtecha. אוקיי okay וגרך אשר בשעריך. vegarecha asher
bish'arecha. ובדיברות האחרונות נאמר ושורך וחמורך וכל בהמתך. uvedibrot ha'acharonot ne'emar veshorecha
vachamorecha vechol behemtecha. So it does it says actually is more broad,
rather it's more specific and more broad. It says כל בהמתך kol
behemtecha but there's also more specific to say שורך וחמורך. shorecha vachamorecha.
אוקיי. okay. והלא שור וחמור בכלל כל בהמה היו, vehalo shor vechamor
bichlal kol behema hayu, they were included in בהמה. behema. Why do
you have to be specific and say שור וחמור shor vechamor on
שבת? Shabbat? ולמה יצאו, velama yatz'u, why were they singled out? לומר
לך, lomar lach, to tell you מה שור וחמור האמור כאן חיה
ועוף כיוצא בהן, mah shor vechamor ha'amur kan chaya ve'of kayotzei vahen,
the same way here it includes all animals
because כל בהמתך, kol behemtecha, certainly בהמתך behemetcha כל בהמתך, kol behemtecha,
all animals are
included. אף כל חיה ועוף כיוצא בהן. af kol chaya ve'of kayotzei
vahen. So by שבת Shabbat it uses very general terms בהמתך, behemetcha,
כל בהמתך kol behemtecha to include all things, and specific terms שור
וחמור shor vechamor to tell you that. Anytime in the תורה torah
it says שור וחמור shor vechamor you should assume it means all
animals. Alright, so the גמרא gemara says אימא בהמה דדיברות ראשונות כלל,
eima behema dedibros rishonos klal, how do you know to read it
that way?
Maybe I should read the first עשרת הדברות aseres hadibros and the
second עשרת הדברות aseres hadibros as one unit and make a כלל
ופרט klal uprat out of it? בהמה דדיברות ראשונות כלל, behema dedibros
rishonos klal, שור וחמורך דדיברא אחרונה פרט. shor vechamorecha dedibra achrona prat.
So first it says בהמה, behema, that's a כלל. klal. שור וחמורך
shor vechamorecha is a פרט prat specific. כלל ופרט אין בכלל אלא
מה שבפרט. klal uprat ein baklal ela ma shebaprat. Maybe I'll limit
it just to a שור וחמור. shor vechamor שור וחמור shor vechamor.
אין, only a שור וחמור, shor vechamor, מידי אחריני לא, lo, nothing
else. אמרנו, amino, וכל בהמתך דדיברות אחרונות. vechol behemtecha dedibros achronos. If
you're going to read them all together, you have בהמתך behemtecha of
the first עשרת הדברות, aseres hadibros, שור וחמור וכל
בהמתך.
shor vechamor
vechol
behemtecha. So that's a כלל
ופרט וכלל. klal prat ukhlal. So חזר וכלל, chozar ukhlal, כלל ופרט
וכלל אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט. klal uprat ukhlal ee ata
dan ela k'ein haprat. So that's going to allow us to say
מה פרט מפורש בעלי חיים, ma prat meforash baalei chayim, that'll still
allow us to say all living things, all living animals, אף כל
בעלי חיים. af kol baalei chayim. So fine, do a כלל ופרט
וכלל, klal prat ukhlal, you still get to the idea of all
animals. Gemara says not necessarily. This is now going to sound familiar.
ואימא מה פרט מפורש דבר שנבילתם מטמאה במגע, ve'eima ma prat meforash
davar shenevilatam metamei bemaga, so only has a שור וחמור, shor vechamor,
maybe the only things that you have to let rest on שבת
shabbos are things that their carcass causes טומאה tumah by touching and
carrying? אף כל דבר שנבילתם מטמאה במגע ובמשא. af kol davar shenevilatam
metamei bemaga uvemasa. אבל עופות לא, aval ofos lo, maybe you don't
have to let your birds rest on שבת, shabbos, which you also
could sort of hear because birds are not like beasts of burden,
right? I mean birds basically are there to be raised either to
be slaughtered or to lay eggs. So anyway, I mean you don't
have to stop your birds from laying eggs on שבת. shabbos. So
the גמרא gemara says אמרנו, amino, אם כן נכתוב רחמנא חד פרט.
im kein niktav rachmana chad prat. If that's what it wanted to
mean, it should have only written one of them. So הי נכתוב?
hei niktav? Which should it have written? אי כתב רחמנא שור, ee
katav rachmana shor, if it had just said שור, shor, הוה אמינא
קרב לגבי מזבח אין. hava amina kareiv legabei mizbeach in. Maybe the
only animal that you'd have to stop working on שבת shabbos are
animals that are brought as sacrifices. That already you hear a little
bit like in terms of the whole ritual, maybe it has more
ritual significance. שאינו קרב לגבי מזבח לא. she'eino kareiv legabei mizbeach lo.
Maybe animals that aren't brought as sacrifices you don't have to let
rest on שבת. shabbos. כתב רחמנא חמור, katav rachmana chamor, it had
to say חמור. chamor. ואי כתב רחמנא חמור, ve'ee katav rachmana chamor,
had it started with חמור, chamor, הוה אמינא קדוש בבכורה. hava amina
kadosh bivchora. Maybe also only animals that have some type of a
קדושה kedusha associated, can become a בכור. bechor. שאין קדוש בבכורה, she'ein
kadosh bivchora, animals like horses and donkeys or excuse me horses and
camels, לא, maybe those wouldn't have to rest on שבת. shabbos. כתב
רחמנא שור. katav rachmana shor. So you need שור וחמור shor vechamor
so that it's not too limiting. But even with שור וחמור, shor
vechamor, how do you know to include birds? So if you just
did a כלל ופרט וכלל klal prat ukhlal you wouldn't include birds.
אלא וכל, ela vechol, fine, you're right, you can't do a כלל
ופרט וכלל klal prat ukhlal to include birds, but וכל בהמתך, vechol
behemtecha, the וכל, vechol, all your animals, that's ריבויה הוא. ribuyah hu.
That's coming to include all animals, even birds. So גמרא gemara says
one minute, וכל היכא דכתיב רחמנא כל ריבויה הוא? vechol heicha dechasiv
rachmana kol ribuyah hu? Every time it says כל kol it means
to be a broad inclusive statement? והא גבי מעשר, veha gabei maaser,
when it comes to מעשר שני, maaser sheni, דכתיב כל, dechasiv kol,
it has the word כל, kol, וקדרשינן ליה בכלל ופרט, vekadorshinnan lei
b'klal uprat, we don't use it to make a broad inclusive statement,
we do a כלל ופרט וכלל. klal prat ukhlal. What is that?
דתניא, detanya,
ונתתה הכסף, venatata hakesef, you should give the money
בכל אשר תאוה נפשך, bechol asher te'aveh nafshecha, כלל, klal, that's a
general statement. בבקר ובצאן, babakar uvatzoan, this is what you use the
מעשר שני maaser sheni money that you bring to ירושלים yerushalayim to
buy and to eat in ירושלים, yerushalayim, okay? With cattle and sheep,
וביין ובשכר, uvayayin uvashachar, and wine and beer, ופרט, uprat, that's concrete
and specific. ובכל אשר תשאלך נפשך, uvechol asher tishalcha nafshecha,
all that your heart desires, חזר וכלל, chozar ukhlal, a general. כלל
ופרט וכלל אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט. klal uprat ukhlal ee
ata dan ela k'ein haprat. So only things that are similar to
the concrete. מה פרט מפורש פרי מפרי וגידולי קרקע, ma prat meforash
pri mipri vegidulei karka, the same way the פרט prat is explicit,
it is a fruit from a fruit. What does that mean? It
means that they are something that actually
produced produce like themselves. Like it would not include רש"י rashi says
the things that would not include would be let's say salt or
mushrooms, fungi, those are things that don't, but these are things, animals
or normal fruit whatever, יין ושכר yayin veshachar whatever, things that come
from grapes. So things that they actually, well the reason it says
פרי מפרי pri mipri is because wine is not the thing, the
actual פרי pri itself, it's taken from the פרי, pri, it's taken
from the grape, okay? But it's still taken from a something that's
seen as a fruit that was produced by a seed, produced by
something, the thing that came before it, as opposed to something that
was always there
like salt or something that was like a fungi. Okay, so it's
פרי מפרי וגידולי קרקע pri mipri vegidulei karka and it grows from
the ground, okay, which is to exclude fish.
And animals don't grow from the ground?
Yeah so תוספות tosafos discusses sometimes the גמרא gemara uses the phrase
גידולי קרקע gidulei karka to include animals cause they eat food from
the ground so they get their nutrients from the ground. Sometimes גידולי
קרקע gidulei karka means very limiting to mean things that literally grow
like fruit and grain etc. But sometimes it's a broad term to
mean animals. What? Terrestrial.
Terrestrial, right, but it would exclude fish. על כל פנים תהוי גידולי
קרקע. Al kol panim tehei gidulei karka. So anyway, the point being
that וכל אשר תשאל נפשך vechol asher tishal nafshecha is still a
כלל. klal. It's not a ריבוי, ribuy, it's not coming to include
everything. So תוס׳ Toss' find: בכל כללא, bakol klala, כל
ריבויא. kol ribuyah. In 'all', that is your normal כלל, klal, וכל
אשר תשאל נפשך. vechol asher tishal nafshecha. Okay, but when it says
וכל, vechol, what was the וכל? vechol? וכל בהמתך. vechol behemtecha. That's
that 'within all'. בכל bakol is a little more limiting than וכל.
vechol. וכל vechol is everything. So that includes all animals. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says: אי בעית אימא, ei ba'is eima, if you
don't like the distinction between בכל bakol and כל, kol, like ברכת
המזון: Birkas HaMazon: בכל מכל כל, bakol mikol kol, right? אי בעית
אימא, ei ba'is eima, if you want, you could say... right, you
know what that's from? וה' ברך את אברהם בכל, V'Hashem berach es
Avraham bakol, and what's it by יצחק? Yitzchak?
By יצחק Yitzchak and
יעקב Yaakov they use either the word כל kol or בכל, bakol,
okay. Anyway, so אי בעית אימא, ei ba'is eima, כל נמי כללא.
kol nami klala. Fine. כל kol is a כלל. klal. It's not
a ריבוי, ribuy, it's a normal כלל. klal. So how do you
get it to include birds? מיהו, mihu, האי כל דהכא ריבויא הוא.
hai kol dehacha ribuyah hu. In general, כל kol is not different
than בכל, bakol,
and כל kol is a כלל. klal. But in this context, וכל
בהמתך, vechol behemtecha,
it's a broad... it's a more broadly inclusive word. How do you
know that? דהוה ליה למיכתב ובהמתך, dehavei lei lemichtav u'behemtecha, כדכתיב בדיברות
ראשונות, kichsiv be'dibros rishonos,
because the extra word כל kol is extra. Because in the first
דיברות dibros it says ובהמתך. u'behemtecha. So here it could have said...
you know, what's the פסוק? pasuk? שורך וחמורך... shorcha v'chamorecha... what is
it? שור וחמור ובהמה. shor v'chamor u'veheimah.
It says וכל בהמה. vechol behemah. That would have been a funny
articulation to say it that way, but anyway, it could have dropped
the word כל kol here. וכתיב וכל בהמתך, u'chsiv vechol behemtecha, שמע
מינה ריבויא. shema minah ribuyah.
So here at least the word כל kol was extra, so וכל
בהמתך vechol behemtecha tells you all animals, including birds. So you have
by the עשרת הדיברות Aseres HaDibros by שבת, Shabbos, the וכל בהמתך
vechol behemtecha tells you... it could have just said ובהמתך, u'behemtecha, it
says וכל בהמתך, vechol behemtecha, tells you all animals. And then because
it says the word שור וחמור, shor v'chamor, it allows you to
learn out that anytime elsewhere it says שור וחמור, shor v'chamor, we
should presume it's referring to all animals. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says: השתא דאמרת וכל ריבויא הוא, hashta d'amart vechol ribuyah hu, now
that you're saying the וכל vechol in this case at least is
a ריבוי, ribuy, ובהמתך דדיברות ראשונות u'behemtecha d'dibros rishonos and שור וחמור
דדיברות אחרונות למה לי? v'shor v'chamor d'dibros achronos lamah li? So if
you just say וכל בהמתך, vechol behemtecha, why do you need in
the דיברות ראשונות dibros rishonos to say ובהמתך? u'behemtecha? Well, obviously you
needed it to say it there or whatever, and why did you
need שור וחמור? shor v'chamor? So the גמרא Gemara says: אמרי, amri,
שור, shor so what we said before: לגמורי שור שור לחסימה. ligmurei
shor shor l'chasimah. This is exactly why וכל בהמתך vechol behemtecha includes
all animals. The specifics are to learn out to other cases. שור
to tell you when it says not to muzzle your ox, it's
not limited to ox. חמור chamor when it says your donkey... the
word here is extra
so that you link the
other cases in the תורה Torah to it. Right. Well, not to
know, no, but to link the other cases to it. לגמורי חמור
חמור לפריקה. ligmurei chamor chamor l'prikah. It says donkey because it says
where you have to unload somebody's donkey that's collapsing. It shouldn't be
limited to donkey. You link it to the case of שבת Shabbos
and it's all animals. ובהמתך, u'behemtecha, when it says ובהמתך u'behemtecha as
opposed to וכל בהמתך, vechol behemtecha, לגמורי בהמתך בהמתך לכלאים. ligmurei behemtecha
behemtecha l'kilayim. The problem of cross-breeding is not limited to, you know,
domesticated animals, it would apply to birds, it would apply to wild
animals. So the גמרא Gemara says: one minute. אי הכי אפילו אדם
נמי ליתסר? ei hachi afilu adam nami lissar? So if the ובהמתך
u'behemtecha and שור וחמור shor v'chamor or whatever tell you all animals,
so then even a person should not be able to plow together
with an animal. That should be a case of כלאים. kilayim. Because
by שבת Shabbos people can't work and animals can't work. So we
should link everything to שבת, Shabbos, and anything that applies to animals
should also apply to people. Therefore, a person... well, a person can't
cross-breed with an animal, that would be an איסור עריות issur arayos
which is חייב מיתה, chayav misah, but a person should be able
to actually plow with an animal... should be, based on this, it
should be forbidden to plow with an animal. Why link that to
plow then? I thought the person has to always...
Well, no, but putting, yoking
yourself in together with your animal. אלמא, alma, so if that's true
this should be forbidden. ואלמא תנן, ve'alma tnan, why do we teach
in a משנה: mishnah: אדם מותר עם כולם לחרוש ולמשוך? adam mutar
im kulam lachrosh v'limshoch? A person can actually attach the plow to
himself and to an animal and plow together with an animal. So
why don't you link it to שבת Shabbos and say, you know,
if it applies to animals, it applies to people, so a person
also is not allowed to plow together with an animal who's of
a different, you know, a different species? So the גמרא Gemara says:
אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, פפונאי, Pappunai, the people from פפונא,
Pappuna, ידעי טעמא דהא מילתא. yad'ei ta'ama d'ha milta. They know how
to explain this. ומנו, u'manu, and who is this? רב אחא בר
יעקב. Rav Acha bar Yaakov. רב אחא בר יעקב. Rav Acha bar
Yaakov. רש"י Rashi points out in another גמרא Gemara it says explicitly
he comes from this place פפונא. Pappuna. So אמר קרא, amar kra,
the verse says: למען ינוח עבדך ואמתך כמוך. lema'an yanuach avdecha va'amasecha
kamocha. By שבת Shabbos it says, so your slave should rest like
you. להנחה הקשתיו ולא לדבר אחר. le'hanacha hikishtiv v'lo l'davar acher. For...
so it says when I have linked these things, you know, your
עבדך ואמתך, avdecha va'amasecha, I have linked them to animals for the
purpose of resting, but I have not linked human beings to animals
for any other purpose. So for all other purposes, you know, animals
are distinct from humans. human beings mentioned in שבת *Shabbos* are only
linked to animals for the purpose of rest, in general humans are
distinct from animals, so therefore even though issues like כלאים kilayim. *kilayim*
or whatever apply to all animals, they don't apply to human beings.
Questions? לשם שמים נתכוון *leshem shamayim nitkaven*. We know the רש"י Rashi
*Rashi*. What's his name under פפונאי *Pappunai*? I don't remember. Okay, I
think it means by what's his name, by עיו *Iyo*. Okay, Sha,
now, let's read, let's read a little bit more. שח רבי חנינא
את רב בן עגיה *shach Rabbi Chanina et Rab ben Agiya*, this
is just such a great little גמרא gemara *Gemara*, we might as
well get a little ahead. שח רבי בן עגיה את רבי חייא
בר אבא *shach Rabbi ben Agiya et Rabbi Chiya bar Abba*. What?
תוספות *Tosfos*? תוספות *Tosfos* says it's telling him it should be לוחות
*luchos*. Yeah, excellent, good point. But we just talked about the, there's
a two sets of לוחות *luchos*. Oh, excellent, excellent, and the שברי
לוחות *shivre luchos* is coming up, right. Okay, מפני מה בדברות הראשונות
לא נאמר בהם טוב tov? ובדברות האחרונות נאמר בהם טוב tov *mipnei
ma badibros harishonos lo ne'emar bahem tov ubidibros ha'achronos ne'emar bahem tov*?
Why by the דברות ראשונות *dibros rishonos* does it not say טוב
tov. *tov*? Because it says, by כיבוד אב ואם *Kibbud Av Va'em*,
it says למען ייטב לך *lema'an yetav lach*, but it doesn't say
it in the דברות אחרונות *dibros achronos*. So you could have just
said why by כיבוד אב ואם *Kibbud Av Va'em* does it say
it in one place or not, but he's obviously pointing to a
bigger question. Like what does that mean that the word טוב tov.
*tov* doesn't appear, right, in the... in the דברות ראשונות *dibros rishonos*?
It only appears in the דברות אחרונות *dibros achronos*. So אמר לה
*amar leh*, עד ad שאתה שואלני למה נאמר בהם טוב tov. *ad
she'attah sho'aleni lama ne'emar bahem tov*, you're asking me why does it
say טוב *tov* only in the דברות אחרונות *dibros achronos* and not
in the first ones, and you're asking me the reason for the
difference, שאלני אם נאמר בהם טוב אם לאו *sho'aleni im ne'emar bahem
tov im lav*. Ask me: does it say טוב *tov* in the
דברות ראשונות *dibros rishonos* and דברות אחרונות *dibros achronos*? שאיני יודע אם
נאמר בהם טוב אם לאו *she'eini yodei'a im ne'emar bahem tov im
lav*. I don't know that! You can totally hear that! No! What
he's saying is, is like, this is so not my area. Like
you're asking me like "Oh, why in the דברות ראשונות *dibros rishonos*
does it say this and not like..." I don't even, like, that's
not stuff that I pay attention to, you know? Ask somebody who
pays attention to that type of a question. All right? So it's
like, this is a classic thing of like: I know הלכה *halacha*,
I don't know אגדתא *aggadata*, like I'm not looking at these questions:
why does it say טוב *tov* here and not טוב *tov* there?
Like I barely know if it says it in one place or
not in the other place. Okay, so זיל לך אצל רבי תנחום
בן חנילאי *zelach etzel Rabbi Tanchum ben Chanilai*. Go to the רבי
תנחום בן חנילאי *Rabbi Tanchum ben Chanilai*, שרגיל אצל רבי יהושע בן
לוי *she'ragil etzel Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi*, he has, he spent time
with רבי יהושע בן לוי *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi*, שהיה בקי באגדה
*she'hayah baki ba'aggadah*. He knows אגדה *aggada*. He pays attention to these
differences, he can go ahead and give you a good reason for
it. It's like the reverse of when רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, there's
one case where רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* suggests an aggadic explanation to
a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, and they say back to him, "You know
what רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*? Go back to נגעים ואהלות *Nega'im ve'Ohalos*."
Go back to הלכה *halacha*. That's your field.
Let the people who know how to do אגדתא *aggadata* do אגדתא
*aggadata*. So here it's the reverse.
He asks this guy, guy says: "That's not my field. Go to
somebody who knows how to do אגדתא *aggadata*." Okay, so אזל לגבי
*azal lagabbei*. Went to him. אמר לה *amar leh*: ממנו לא שמעתי
*mimmennu lo shamati*. So he says, you know, he went to רבי
תנחום בן חנילאי *Rabbi Tanchum ben Chanilai*, who would
learn
from רבי יהושע בן לוי *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi*.
He said, "I didn't hear an explanation of this from רבי יהושע
בן לוי *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi*, אלא ela כך אמר לי שמואל
בר נחום אחי אמו של רב אחא בריה דרבי חנינא *aval kach
amar li Shmuel bar Nachum achi immo sheRab Acha brei deRabbi Chanina*..."
So interesting, all these people that are named that you normally don't
hear about. I guess that's because they're more from the אגדי *aggadic*
field. ואמרי לה *ve'amri lah*, and some say אבי אמו של רב
אחא בריה דרבי חנינא *avi immo sheRab Acha brei deRabbi Chanina*, and
some say it's the father's mother of רב אחא *Rab Acha* the
son of רבי חנינא *Rabbi Chanina*. So anyway, what is the reason?
הואיל וסופן להשתבר *ho'il vesofan lishhtaber*. I wonder though, because the טוב
*tov* is said by the whole כיבוד אב ואם *Kibbud Av Va'em*
here, and you have a lot here about the father and the
mother, right? שמואל בר נחום אחי אמו *Shmuel bar Nachum achi immo*,
right, and some say אבי אמו *avi immo*. Anyway, הואיל וסופן להשתבר
*ho'il vesofan lishhtaber*. It doesn't say למען ייטב לך *lema'an yetav lach*
by the first דברות *dibros* because they were going to be broken.
So you didn't want the, so the גמרא *Gemara* says back, "וכי
משתבר מאי הוי *vechi mishhtaber mai hava*?" So what? There's a lot
of important things that got broken. אנכי ה' אלהיך *Anochi Hashem Elokecha*
got broken in the first דברות *dibros*. So why should, so what's
the big deal? So it would have said טוב *tov*. אמר רב
אשי *amar Rav Ashi*: חס ושלום פסקה טובה מישראל *chas veshalom paskah
tovah miYisrael*. Because that would have symbolized that there would have been
an end, like, that good, that there would have been... it would
cease amongst ישראל *Yisrael*, right? So therefore the symbolic thing, I mean
obviously you have שם ה' *shem Hashem*, all these things breaking, but
the idea that טוב *tov*, good, would have broken would have been
symbolically, you know, too heavy. אמר רבי יהושע *amar Rabbi Yehoshua*. So
רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* says, so as was correctly pointed out by
הלל *Hillel*, important גמרא *Gemara* to read right on י"ז בתמוז *Shiva
Asar BeTammuz*, which is, you know, about the... when the לוחות *luchos*
were broken. אמר רבי יהושע *amar Rabbi Yehoshua*: הרואה ט' בחלומו *haro'eh
tes bechalomo*, somebody who sees the letter ט' *tes* in his dream,
סימן יפה לו *siman yafeh lo*. It's a good סימן *siman*. Because
presumably it signifies טוב *tov*. מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama*? What reason? אילימא
משום דכתיב טוב *im mishum dechtiv tov*? Because it said טוב *tov*.
אימא eima *eima*, how about there's other things that start with ט'
*tes*? וטאטאתיה במטאטא השמד *vetetei'ah bematatei hashmad*. I will sweep them out
with the broom of destruction. So that's a lot of ט' *tes*
in that פסוק *pasuk*! So it says, no, חד ט' קאמרינן *chad
tes ka'amrina*. No, no, you just saw one ט' *tes*. There's too
many ט' *tes* there, that's a... so אימא *eima*: טומאתה בשוליה *tum'atah
beshuleiha*. It's also here, these are actually פסוקים *pesukim* also about חורבן
*churban*. It's actually quite interesting for reading in י"ז בתמוז *Shiva Asar
BeTammuz*, right? It says that, you know, her defilement is on her...
the... the... the skirt. So that's also obviously a פסוק *pasuk* about
destruction and חורבן *churban*. ט' ב' Tet Bet, קאמינא. No, no, I
didn't mean just saw the word טית. tet. You saw ט' ב',
so you saw the word טוב? Okay. So the גמרא says, yeah,
I guess if you saw the whole word טוב it would have
been too obvious. אימא טבעו בארץ שעריה. tavu ba'aretz she'areha. It's its
gates sunk into the ground, again a פסוק of destruction, also of
חורבן הבית. churban habayis. אלא fine. הואיל ופתח בו הכתוב לטובה תחילה.
hoil upatach bo hakasav letova techila. Because the טית, tet, the first
time the letter טית tet appears in the תורה Torah is in
the word טוב. That's pretty cool, huh? מבראשית mibreishis עד וירא אלהים
את האור כי טוב, vayar Elokim es ha'or ki tov, לא כתיב
ט'. lo ksiv tet. So the first time the letter טית tet
appears in the תורה, Torah, it says טוב. So therefore the letter
טית tet by itself, yes, there are other טיתים tetim in other
words, but the טית tet by itself is more linked with the
idea of טוב. Okay, ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, v'amar Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi, הרואה הספד בחלומו, haroeh hesped bechalomo, חסו עליו מן השמים
ופדוהו. chasu alav min hashamayim u'fduhu. So it doesn't mean a person's
gonna die, it means a person was gonna die and then he
was saved, okay, and they had compassion from heaven. והני מילי בכתבא,
vehanay mili bechtava, but that's only not if you heard yourself being
eulogized, but רש"י says it means but apparently you saw the word
written. You saw like you saw on a piece
of paper in your dream the word הספד. hesped. Okay, so then
that means that you were somehow saved. All right, so we will
pick up with this tomorrow and talking about some of the parameters
of כלאים.